We approved your questions.
No.
We approved it, yes.
I think you're getting one from
me.
You didn't develop it.
Sorry.
You debriefed it.
Oh. Oh, sorry.
That should be a formal statement.
Yes, okay. Sorry.
Mr Byford, how are you?
Good, Mr Chairman.
We are in your hands.
You watched the
presentations from Mr Blakely and-
Mm
... Dr McDonald.
So if you want to make some comments, we're in your hands, but I think members will
have some questions as well.
Thank you.
Thank you, Mr Chairman and Committee, for the chance to
give evidence.
I've reflected on the appearance of Nick Blakely and
Alison McDonald for the Education and Workforce Committee on the 4th of
March 2026,
and their answers to my questions about the biometric
capability upgrade in light of all of the information that
has since come to light.
And I remain of the view that they misled the Education and
Workforce Committee, and by extension, misled
Parliament.
I'd received information about the biometric capability upgrade
in three separate OIA releases over the
previous two years,
and had been alerted to problems with the
project by a source.
My questions considered and drafted in advance
were,
there's been a number of reports, we understand, independent reviews that have
warned about delivery risks.
I wonder if you could tell us what the key risks are that were
identified and whether any milestones have slipped
in implementation so far.
The answer from Alison McDonald, and you've seen the transcript,
can best be described as obfuscation and omission.
I took from her answer that there was a lot of uncertainty about the
project,
but that it was still ongoing.
We now know that when those non-answers were being given, the
project had been closed down after the minister commissioned an
independent investigation,
and the biometric capability upgrade had been, for some time,
a highly sensitive matter between the minister and her
department.
I then asked why the full review reports had not been released
publicly.
The answers from Alison McDonald and Nick Blakely indicated there were a
number of reviews, and they weren't sure why they had not been released,
and they would look into that.
The clear implication that I took from this whole exchange is that the project
was still live.
In fact, the project had been discontinued.
Mm.
The minister had called in an external consultant who'd written a damning
report.
Mm.
My view is that this is not terribly complicated.
I asked some very specific questions about a named project,
what were the key risks identified in a series of reports and whether any
milestones had slipped in implementation.
We now know the reports identified many very significant
risks, and to say that implementation milestones had
slipped is an understatement.
But you wouldn't know any of that from the answers given by Alison
McDonald and Nick Blakely.
I think objectively, their answers were misleading.
While both of them have expressed remorse that this was the effect of their answers
and stated it was not their intention to mislead, the fact is that
their answers misled the committee.
Two very senior public servants in one of the biggest government departments
chose not to be forthcoming in response
to direct and specific questioning at one of Parliament's
annual review hearings.
Thank you.
I would like to address briefly the contention that the biometric capability
upgrade was subject to budget and commercial sensitivity
or secrecy. On both grounds, there are simple ways of
dealing with the problem, including offering a private briefing for the committee
or just noting that a certain issue cannot be discussed at this time, but a
briefing can be arranged at a later date.
Whatever their reason, Alison McDonald and Nick Blakely chose not to
answer the committee's questions in a way that was fair, accurate
or substantive.
Their primary intent may have been to avoid discussing the matter,
but the effect of their decision was to mislead.
And I do not think it's credible that they, as senior public servants
appearing in an annual review hearing, would not have understood that
at the time.
I believe it's untenable, regardless of whether it's a
matter of budget secrecy, commercial secrecy, or just
keeping something politically sensitive under wraps,
for public servants to dissemble and obfuscate
when asked specific questions by a select committee in
an annual review hearing.
It is misleading Parliament.
Thank you very much. Okay, Duncan.
Just a preliminary question.
You've seen the transcript of the last hearing of this committee.
Was it-
Clear to you that those two MBIE
staff members knew that your question was aimed at the
Biometric Capability Upgrade program?
Well, I explicitly used that description of the
program in my
opening question. So my assumption is they must have.
Given your comments you've just said, I guess the question for this committee is,
we weren't there in that committee, so we couldn't see the interaction, and it's
not the same on video.
Is it your view that
whatever the motive,
the intention was to
not answer that question accurately?
So when I think back on the hearing, I
have to conclude that the intention was
not to be forthcoming with the committee. The motive, we can speculate.
There might have been a number of motives, and that's for you to decide.
But my
reading of what happened in that meeting and their answers was that
they
deliberately chose not to be forthcoming in their
answers on that question.
That's all.
Mr. Peters.
When or on what date was your first
OIA request made?
Sorry, Mr. Peters, could you repeat that for me?
You mentioned that you had made a number of OIA-
OIA
... requests. I'm asking, when was your first one made? What was the date of it?
I'm sorry, I haven't got the date in front of me, but they ranged from late
2024 to early 2026.
And how many there were?
Three.
What was the gap between them?
It was in the order of
six, seven months between them.
But you could furnish the Select Committee with that information.
I can provide, yes.
What changed between the first and the last OIA request?
The
commentary about the
Biometric Capability upgrade included
quite detailed descriptions of
reviews that had been done and
kind of little snapshots of progress.
But it wasn't possible from what was released to discern any
kind of particular pattern or to get anything like what we now know as the full
story.
And
it was really only being alerted by a source
who had been able to piece together the fact that this
was a protracted, long-running, and highly
problematic project within the department that really alerted
me to that.
So the nature of your complaints, you learned not from their OIA
answers-
Yeah
... but from later, and outside information, and later developments.
Correct.
Okay.
Yeah, okay. Yeah. We'll go Parmjeet then Ricarda.
So in that information that was released to you-
Mm-hmm
... were there parts that were redacted, and was there any reason given, like
commercially sensitive, so that we know
something was there behind the scenes?
No, there was not.
Nothing.
No, to the best of my knowledge,
there wasn't any redacted material about the project.
And so nothing was hidden for commercial sensitive reasons.
No.
Thank you.
Ricarda.
Yeah. Mr. Blakely told us that one of the reasons that he came to the
conclusion that, for example, couldn't talk about the project is that
there was an official Information Act request released later in March that withheld
information on the grounds of commercial sensitivity.
But I am assuming that you were, in your OIA system, in a range of
issues way beyond simply whether the project was alive or
otherwise, right?
Yes, these were broad-ranging OIAs that included material about the upgrade.
So what do you make of the responses by Mr.
Blakely where he compared, basically,
the OIA requests as a way to justify not
being forthcoming with the status of the project?
Well, as a member of Parliament's Education and Workforce Committee,
it would be my expectation that when asked
specifically about a named project,
public servants would
answer directly. And if there were things that they couldn't
discuss and
they
could say at the time, "Well, this is a matter that's
under discussion. We're not in a
position to publicly discuss this right now.
But a time will come when documents will be proactively released, or we
could come back and brief the committee at another time." That's normal
practice.
Yeah.
So.
What did you make of post-hearing question 63 and
84 and their answers?
And the fact that on those questions, the BCU project was explicitly
mentioned, yet at no point in the process
MBIE took an opportunity to clarify the status of the project
when writing those answers.
Well, I think that those written answers sort of compounded the
problem, really. And
it was
only when
the whole thing kind of blew up publicly that
they decided to
revisit those answers and come back to the committee.
Do you think that undermines the argument we've heard that when the oral
questions were put forward in the public hearing, that it wasn't clear that it was
about the BCU when it was made clear in the post-hearing questions that it was?
Well, there was no doubt in my mind in
the March 3 hearing that they understood that
we were talking about the biometric capability upgrade.
If you read the transcript, my recollection at the time, and I
specifically used names the project.
So that does not seem credible to me.
Very unsatisfactory. Scott?
So, we've had at hearings
last week from Dr. McDonald and Mr.
Blakely,
apologies for what they told us
were
omissions rather than intentional
or deliberate misleadings.
But your contention very much so, I just want to get this sort of
confirmed, is that it was deliberate rather than
an innocent act of omission.
Yes. And I'm conscious that this is really for your
deliberation. But my view is that
I'm sure from everything that we've heard, it wasn't their primary
motivation to deceive the committee.
I'm sure that's the case.
But,
I also believe they
knowingly made a decision not to answer those questions
properly because they didn't want to share the information publicly, and there's a
number of reasons that they've said, and we can speculate
may have been why they didn't want to be open and forthcoming about it.
But nevertheless, they chose a course of action that had the effect
of misleading Parliament,
and that to me is the nub of it.
And, as senior public servants appearing in scrutiny week,
it's not credible to think that they didn't understand that,
that that approach would have misled the committee.
Okay.
I'm final, yes. Just a bit of clarification on my previous question.
Mm-hmm.
So the information you received in OIA, that means are you now
100% sure that that information is complete-
Um-
... based on what we know now?
So the information is-
If nothing was redacted, so-
It's not complete in any sense because these were
documents,
a small number of documents among many.
Mm-hmm.
And, they don't give a coherent or complete picture of what was happening.
They're small pieces of the overall picture.
So that means you are saying that even in those OIAs,
there was some,
if I can use the word deliberate, act
of not providing some information and instead of providing the document and
redacting it?
No, I wouldn't make that claim because, we weren't in those
OIAs. We weren't prosecuting the question of this project in the way that
we did it at the select committee hearing.
They were more kind of general questions.
Okay.
And small bits of information emerged.
So,
I wouldn't make that claim.
Okay.
Okay. Sorry. Duncan.
Just to get, just get that clear, one thing.
You're saying that in every respect you have met, you believe they comply with the
OIA request requirements?
In relation to the three OIA requests where we
received information, I don't have any reason to believe that they did not
comply.
Okay, so your core proposition is they misled the committee, but do you
think it was deliberate?
That's very good.
I think it was deliberate that they chose not to be
forthcoming. They may have had any range.
We can speculate about what their motives may have been.
Okay.
But they deliberately, and I believe knowingly,
chose not to be forthcoming with Parliament's Education and Workforce
Committee.
Mm-hmm.
Okay. Ricardo.
Just come back to the OIAs that you did.
At any point
in your request, did you explicitly include questions around the status of the
project?
And questions that would've revealed just the
status at the time?
I don't have the document in front of me, so I don't want to-
That's fair
... answer specifically about that.
But I could come back to the committee on that. Yes.
Any WPQs?
No.
Yes, please.
We'll do Mr. Peters, then you, Marama.
Yeah.
Have you taken any legal advice on their behavior?
I have not.
Sort of our job.
Well, no. This parliament's record has been to never ask the right question
on those sort of matters.
Mm-hmm.
But, well, do you imagine this shades into illegality?
Mr. Peters, I suppose my
approach has been to consider that this is the
most appropriate and powerful forum to-
Right
... to deal with this question of misleading Parliament, and that's why I made
the complaint.
Well, that's one forum.
Mm-hmm.
There are others.
That's true. Marama, you know.
Just, thank you.
You use words like obfuscation and dissemble, and those words are...
I mean,
they're big words. They show intention.
Then you go on to say, but you don't believe that they intended to mislead.
What was their intention? What do you think they
intended to do? What message do you think they wanted to leave?
What was their intention?
You say deliberately choosing not to be forthcoming.
Yes.
Which is all a bit
gray to me anyway. I mean, I get the words, but I'm just
trying to... It's a bit too gray, and we need something a little bit more-
Yeah. You need a-
So
I have ultimately no way of knowing what their intention was.
We can only speculate. And the distinction I've tried to make is that-
I don't know what their motive is.
It may have been, they talked about commercial secrecy, budget secrecy.
I suspect that just an unwillingness to talk about
something that is politically sensitive, that is currently
private, they're unwilling to discuss it.
But it may have been any mix of those factors.
But the key issue, I think, is that they
chose not to be forthcoming. They must have known
that that would have had the effect of misleading this committee, even
if that wasn't their primary
motive or intention.
What I don't understand is how blasé it all was.
You wouldn't have known that the program was
basically a disaster.
No, it did.
It was dead.
It was not a project.
It had been a shocker.
It was a dead project.
Yeah.
An expensive one.
As Monty Python says, "Bereft of life."
Yeah, that's right.
It's just resting.
They gave it the illusion.
It's resting, yeah.
The waste of money.
Well, there's that, too.
Waste.
But I was trying to make a joke.
What a waste.
So
then, Parmjeet.
So there was reference in the previous hearing about the pack
and that the information about the BCU wasn't included in the pack.
Mm.
Do you think that that, in your words, was also they deliberately chose not to
be forthcoming by omitting to put that
information in the pack, the information about the BCU?
So I have no information to base a view on that.
And I
heard your discussion about that in the last meeting.
But I suppose my
judgment would be that this was an
extremely sensitive issue internally within the
department and its senior echelons of the department and their
relationship with one of their ministers.
And
there had been stories by Jill Bonnar of Radio New
Zealand about this matter. It would be
unthinkable to me that it would not have been one of the issues in the
three preparation sessions they had, that would not have been
a focus of their-
Feels a bit odd.
Yeah.
Feel free to answer this however you like.
You were Associate Immigration up until '23,
right?
Was this in your belly work?
No.
Oh, you didn't have anything to do with it?
That's probably good for you.
But I just wondered if you had any...
Really, as ministers come and go, and they carry information they know.
Yeah.
Okay, fine. Fair enough. Okay, we'll go-
Well, if you didn't, who did?
The minister, probably.
Principal minister.
He was the associate.
Yeah.
Who was the minister?
Oh, it was Michael Wood.
Michael Wood, and then Andrew Little.
And Andrew Little.
Yeah.
Because we could get-- No, let's not get him for that.
Let's not. He was busy doing other things.
He was other things going on. All right.
Thank you.
We'll do one more from Parmjeet, then I think we'll wind it up, because we're
coming to the end of the-
So, Phil, that was a public session,
so you have seen what was said in the last hearing.
And you were saying that they chose to not disclose that
information. But in two questions that I asked last time,
I asked them if there were any discussions within MBI about whether the committee
should be informed of the cancellation of this project or not.
The answer was, "No active decision." And then I asked if anybody
advised them of not to disclose that information.
They said, basically, nobody advised them.
So you are saying it's deliberate.
But for something to happen deliberate, that means there has to be some kind of
discussion beforehand, right? That this should not be
disclosed. So what do you make of that?
Well,
I think those discussions within a government agency
can happen
with varying degrees of formality.
There doesn't have to be a written directive, "Do not discuss this matter
publicly at all." But understandings can arise between the
key personalities that this is a matter that's extremely sensitive,
and we don't want it in the public domain.
So it could be somewhere on that spectrum, I would say.
So that means they are individually responsible because there is no directive or
no active discussion about it, individually responsible for
misinforming, rather than it being a
whole management kind of issue.
Perhaps, yeah.
Okay. I think
Immigration, New Zealand returns. Thank you.
Cool.
We'll clear the room, if that's okay.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.